This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[music]
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Adi Narayan. Today's
episode is about the evolution of
JavaScript and how its new features can
allow developers to make their apps more
performant and optimized for
sophisticated browsers.
Here to talk about it is Will Sentence.
He's a seasoned educator and one of the
founders of Codesmith, which runs a
full-stack and machine learning training
programs. He's also a visiting fellow at
Oxford University working on AI and has
created a course on the hard parts of
JavaScript, very relevant to our
conversation, and you can find this on
frontendmasters.com.
Earlier in his career, he was one of the
founders of Icecom, a tool which allowed
developers to add P2P video and audio
chats to their websites. Will, welcome
to Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you for having me, Adi. It's a
pleasure to be here.
Is there anything that I missed out that
you'd like to add to that introduction?
Yeah, only that now I work out of South
Park Commons, a community in San
Francisco, where I work on embodied AI
developer tooling. So, this is the
transition of software engineering from
the, I guess, virtual world to its
potential in the physical world. And so,
building the tools, the Twilios, the
Stripes, the MongoDB equivalents for the
physical revolution of AI that I think
is coming.
100% and it's a topic that we hope to
cover in a future episode, for sure.
Absolutely.
So, let's get started. Will, you've been
living and breathing JavaScript, so to
speak, for a long time, and you've been
teaching folks how to get really good at
it. To get started, can you give us a
brief history of JavaScript and how it
came about and how it evolved?
Absolutely. So, I think most people
listening will know that JavaScript
started from a 1995 era, created in a
very short period of time, something
like 10 days, supposedly, and never
really was expected to be the home of
all modern dynamic web applications that
it's become. By the early 2000s,
creative folk behind web browsers were
starting to realize the limit of
plugins, so things like Java applets
that were the at that point default, or
Flash, that were the default techniques
for adding interactivity to a web
application, and started pushing the
limits of JavaScript, both with existing
features and starting to introduce new
features. So, one of the pioneers of
that, of course, is Google Maps, as I'm
sure, again, many of your listeners will
know, may even have a memory of first
interacting with the web browser, a
pretty amazing moment, I think. My first
light bulb moment was with a site called
Netvibes. Sure, almost nobody remembers
it, but it was a dynamic home page with,
again, draggable components, something
that we now take for granted, but back
in 2004 was a really significant moment
in what you could imagine could be built
within this environment, the web
browser. Fast forward to today, and the
language JavaScript is now a much more
mature language. That's a combination of
the TC39 committee that has responded to
needs from the community for nearly
decades now of being responsive to the
community and adding features, but it's
also a coherence of browsers. So,
browser developers backed by pretty
substantial organizations working
incredibly hard to evolve their
architecture under the hood to make sure
that even as huge amount of features
have been added, and web applications
have become far heavier in the workloads
they're handling, the browser is still
able to handle that, and has the
capacity to handle it, both the
architectural decisions around it, but
also the features available to
developers in JavaScript. And that's not
just JavaScript, it's also web browser
APIs that are part of the experience. I
think a lot of us might sometimes get
confused what is JavaScript and what are
web browser APIs, things like fetch or
the access to the camera or local
storage, all being essentially browser
features and not developed by the ECMA
committee, that's the group that works
on JavaScript itself. But they've all
started to play hand in hand together
much more. So, while today many people
write some abstraction level above,
maybe TypeScript, maybe React, at the
core JavaScript is now a fairly mature
and stable language. What we can talk
about is its additive nature and
append-only system because while a
Python or a Java might have a version
release cycle where at some point a
previous version is deprecated,
JavaScript within the browser needs to
be backwards compatible within reason
all the way back to 1995. And so that's
the constraint in which this language
has always been evolving and I think
we'll probably talk about some of the
decisions that have been made that are a
result of that.
100%. And I guess that constraint as
it's called don't break the web
constraint, given that sort of a
constraint that exists, what has that
led to? What kind of improvements have
the guardians of JavaScript not been
able to make because of that constraint?
Yeah, I mean there's probably many we
don't realize without looking at the
committee notes or the conversations
going behind the scenes, but some that
really surfaced to public knowledge, one
was 2018 I think, pretty notorious or
not notorious significant moment when
the JavaScript developers increasingly
recognized that what we might call user
land, so that's libraries developed by
the public open source community, so
things like Lodash, had many functions
that you would perhaps take for granted
in other languages like Python,
developed by the community, but not
available within JavaScript itself. So,
particularly array methods. That was
around the time when functional paradigm
and thinking about data as something to
be transformed from function to function
without maybe directly mutating became
really demanded by the community. And
so, mapping, flattening, type
higher-order functions became something
that was requested. And in 2018, it
reached the point where a flatten array
built-in method was proposed. Great,
sounds good until you realize that there
was a MooTools library that was still
being used by thousands of applications
that already had a built-in flatten
property available to developers to use
directly on their arrays through the
prototype by mutating it. And that would
now be overridden if a flatten method
was added at the language primitive
level, the standard library level. And
so, after much debate, including
potentially calling it smoosh, which
would have been much better name.
Exactly. And they came up with
smooshgate. The agreement came to create
a flat array method. And when you think
about wanting your method names to
reflect their action, flatten is more
appropriate. But in the end, flat was
chosen because the legacy of previous
libraries that still needed to be
compatible with restricted what was
really available. And that is the again
guiding principle of JavaScript
developers. So, I think one of the most
significant steps the language creators
took was introducing therefore an
entirely new primitive known as a
symbol. And I actually did a new version
of the hard parts of JavaScript a few
months ago and did a whole section on
symbols. They're one of the most
counterintuitive constructs that you
could possibly imagine until you realize
that they are designed essentially as a
workaround for not adding new properties
to objects where there is a chance of
collision. And I don't mean collision in
the hash map sense, but just collision
of a name within JavaScript itself with
existing libraries or existing
developers custom properties
[clears throat] added to an object.
Meaning that if you are a developer and
you've written code that's going to loop
through all your publicly available
properties on your object and suddenly
there's a new property added by
JavaScript's core team, then suddenly
you're going to be displaying a lot more
than you expected on the UI. And so a
new primitive was introduced, the
symbol, that gives JavaScript and then
also developers through meta programming
techniques the ability to add new
features to objects without the risk of
clashing on existing properties. And
this is the result of having a language
that needs to be backwards compatible.
There ain't no this is 2.7. If you're
using it, you need to use the existing
features, but if you want to use the new
features, you need to accept the entire
code base will be deprecated unless you
upgrade to the new version. Doesn't
exist in JavaScript. Fascinating
constraint has led to things like
symbols that allow you to add properties
that are only accessible through certain
entry points within the code, meaning
that the change in ability, the change
in behavior of JavaScript is possible,
but not without conscious decision by
developer to use it. No unconscious
accidental interaction with it.
In terms of the constraint, is it right
for me to summarize that right at the
beginning you had a lot of userland
libraries like Lodash, like Moment, that
do fairly standard things like
formatting time, being able to format
strings and so forth, which people have
gotten so used to that it's impossible
for TC39 to introduce these fairly
standard features into the language
without essentially forcing people to
stop using those libraries. Is that
accurate?
I think it's accurate. I think at this
point everybody in development is
excited by the new built-in temporal
feature of JavaScript that will allow a
more modern interface for time because
the moment library, while there's
lightweight versions, is quite a heavy
library just for access to time features
that work as you might expect that tie
to the ISO standards for thinking about
time. And so, yeah, the changes still
get made, but the day that all
developers move off moment and use the
temporal object directly, I mean,
that'll be a surprise because your code
base, I mean, this is what we'll talk
about later, I'm sure, but the
individual JavaScript features that you
might benefit from switching to new
vanilla features, new built-in standard
library features, is a question less of
performance and more of maintenance. The
gains to maintenance are potentially
significant, but the legacy dependencies
of these libraries may sit across
millions of lines of code, and so
switching out is no small feat.
Agree. Now, what actually led TC39 to
start absorbing these userland patterns
into the language? Was it mainly driven
by performance, security concerns, or
was it a case of it's high time we do
this now or never?
Yeah, that's a great question. So, I
think we can agree that JavaScript's
standard library is still surprisingly
thin. So, engineers still struggle with,
or did until very recently, one of the
most is deep cloning or immutable
objects, and I think the hack has been
the JSON.parse stringify step that maybe
we're all familiar with, but that's a
performance hit, undoubtedly. And that
comes again from this concern, do not
break the web, this defining principle
that they've experienced for so long.
However, because the library is so thin,
the community has developed great tools
to fix that gap. I think the way that
TC39 thinks about it is if the community
develops almost as an experimental
approach, then at a certain point, we
see the demand is significant enough
that we then add and develop that
feature ourselves. So, I think in some
cases it's performance with deep
cloning, I think we've got finely
structured clone, but that is definitely
to overcome the performance hit of using
either a low dash library, which is
perhaps less of a performance hit or
more likely a JSON parse JSON.stringify.
For others, I think it's a
responsiveness to the community. Let it
be fought out in almost user land as
R&D. And then TC39 absorbs the patterns
once the community proves they're
essential. It's almost a filtration
system. So, I think performance is
important, but also if you are a
language that is used so broadly in so
many different domains, not just the
browser of course, but node and bun and
everywhere else, you can use your
community and the development of their
own libraries as a filtration system.
What really emerges as the standard
universal need? Okay, it's been around
for long enough, now we integrate it.
That makes a lot of sense. Do they end
up waiting for too long though? So,
something new came up, everyone started
using it, and you've waited so long that
people are just going to be resistant to
switch to anything new.
I think the answer is definitely yes
before 2015. I think since 2015, the
release cycle is much more reasonable.
And now, I think it's fair to say that
you actually see features shaped at a
sustainable rate where there is enough
awareness that you're what we're calling
robotics the end effector, in this case
the browser or the node environment,
they also have changes. So, the needs
come and go. So, patience around that is
a suitable thing when you're defining a
standard library that is used in so many
different end effectors. But equally,
there needs to be a steady regular pace.
It was only in 2015 that that really
started. You started getting yearly
releases. Until 2015, if there were
yearly releases, they they thought about
as a mature cycle, and 2015 was when I
think the shift really happened. So,
what you describe as the slow pace, I
think that's really something that's no
longer an issue, but it really was
before ES2015, for sure.
Makes sense. And thank you for
clarifying that. As an instructor who
sees thousands of developers, do you
find folks eager to try out these new
features, or is there a tendency to go
with what works because there's so much
code out there that still uses the user
land libraries to discontinue using that
and not try out the new stuff?
I think the former
when people are really looking for a
performance upgrade. Where a feature
adds a serious performance upgrade,
things like structured clone, things
like the temporal object, for want of a
better term, when it's released a
temporal feature, I think you see that.
Performance gains are so often, within
the given language itself, secondary to
all the other performance killers that
step ahead of unoptimized JavaScript,
right? So, you know, I talk to engineers
in the team, but obviously alums of
CodeSmith working enormous code bases,
and far more of an issue for them are
things like unoptimized fetch requests
that pull an entire example. I was
talking to an engineer who works at a
sports data company, and they pull a
single player, and they get their entire
team history. They get their entire game
history. They get their entire
interaction with other players in
different games, and that's the API
available. And so, far more often, the
pressure is to fix the fetch than it is
to improve an edge case performance gain
that comes from switching from a Lodash
to a pure JavaScript feature. There are
exceptions to that, of course, but in
terms of performance, I think it tends
to be secondary. Now, where I think
there's a lot of interest, of course, is
library creators. So, when you're a
library creator, the ability to use
native features that are more performant
and easier to write and easier to reason
with, that's where you start to see a
change. And I think you see that also
over years when some of the features
built in are super similar to other
languages. So, I think the await feature
is one of the most broadly adopted
feature of JavaScript. And not a
surprise that it's a feature that is
very analogous to other languages. And
also a feature that reverts the order of
control to give the developer at the
very least a sense that the code is
executing line by line down the page and
not one of the hardest things to reason
about, which is a function definition
being passed to a function call and for
you to understand as a developer that
somehow that function definition is not
going to be executed until some point at
a later stage when some actions in my
own happens and only then is that
function called. And by the way, you
better have any work you want to happen
on that call be inside that function
definition. That is the most challenging
mental model for people to get their
heads around. Whereas, once you
introduce an await keyword, it's code
linearly down the page until you hit
await, do the async task, get the result
back, and then code continues down the
page from there. The problem is, of
course, that does not reflect the actual
execution pattern. If that await is
within a function, an async function,
then the code outside that async
function's call will continue. And your
awaited code will not execute until
later until all global code's finished
executing. So, yeah, that's the problem
when you have really appealing
abstractions, really appealing new
features, and when they're not
understood, there's a huge disconnect
between how it really works and maybe
what it looks like on the page. And
that's when you get those bugs that
unless you have under the hood
understanding, and that's my passion of
mine is to give people that under the
hood understanding, you're not going to
be able to debug.
Makes a lot of sense. I think it's
useful for listeners to also understand
JavaScript as a language, it's always
been the situation where you can write
whatever you want, and it's the job of
the engine to fix it, to essentially
save your bad code. And that's shifting
now, right? It will help to sort of
understand why this tendency to save bad
code exists within JavaScript.
Yeah, and it is shifting. So, I think
from the very start, there was an
inclination to have JavaScript be a very
flexible language. There's a couple of
reasons for that. One, I think it was a
scripting language in theory for people
who were primarily thinking about the
pixels on the page or communicating text
on the page to be able to add a little
bit of dynamism. That's it. That was its
goal. So, from the start, it had a very
flexible structure because it's a
scripting language. It's not designed to
be a robust end-to-end production
application development language. Now,
obviously, that's no longer the case,
even close, but it was where it started.
Secondly, JavaScript's most typical
environment in which it runs, the web
browser, is a messy set of APIs for
interacting with the page, the DOM, the
document, for other features, text, HTTP
messages from the network. These are all
external interfaces that again, from
early on, were across many different
browsers implemented in many different
ways. And so, the hope was that if you
let JavaScript be flexible, that
including, by the way, automatically
coercing types, data types from one to
another, but at that interface between
the JavaScript land and the web browser,
the DOM, the network, that maybe
JavaScript could automatically help you
coerce things that came off the web
browser as text strings into numbers.
And, of course, in theory, in a small
scale, that might be quite helpful. In
practice, at real application scale,
that becomes extremely difficult and
dangerous. And that's where TypeScript
and or more generally type checking at
every boundary between JavaScript and
any IO becomes vital. But the underlying
principle was coming from a relatively
informed place. It just isn't suited to
this type of using that language as it
is now for complex applications.
And I guess that having it flexible
really helped in its growth, right? The
fact that pretty much 100% of the web is
based on JavaScript or TypeScript is
testament to the fact that this was such
an easy language. The entry barrier was
pretty low and it was pretty forgiving
for the most part.
I think that's right. Forgiving in the
sense that your
error is handed to the user, right? As
opposed to at a compile time stage. I
think it's also gave it a really rough
reputation. My sense would be that it's
almost we call it syntactic sugar.
Syntactic sugar is really dangerous
because it can create this artificial
sense of understanding. I'm able to
technically write it and follow it, but
as soon as you hit a more complex edge
case, let's think about the event loop.
The event loop is a actually fairly
clear model once it's explicitly
defined. And yet, if you only see the
JavaScript runtime and you only see your
code technically not erroring because an
undefined returned or an undefined value
doesn't cause a compile error, then you
might think it's working. Or you might
at the very least not hit the block and
feel the error and then try another
tool. But in practice, until you have
that mental model of the event loop, the
callback queue, the call stack, you're
really flying blind. Once you have them
though, I do think JavaScript with the
flexibility is really appealing. If you
have a really strong mental model of
this language, and it's why I have
taught my workshops on it for years and
I long ago switched to teaching neural
networks and AI model, but I still come
back to teaching JavaScript because you
have a a of the core principles of
programming languages implemented in
JavaScript. You have an event loop, you
have an asynchronous IO design, you have
queuing, you have a way of at least
thinking about inheritance. It's not
native classical inheritance, but you
have a way of thinking about it with a
prototype chain. You have flexible and
interesting ways of thinking about
persisting data between different
function calls. You have closure to do
that, or you have other patterns you can
use. And the variety actually does
become really appealing as you say. The
flexibility becomes really appealing,
but I would just strongly say only once
you have a clear mental model.
Otherwise, you hear people being very
critical of JavaScript because the
flexibility where you don't understand
under the hood is a curse. But when you
do understand under the hood, it becomes
an asset. You can say, "Hey, our team's
going to really follow an
object-oriented pattern. Yes, we know
it's not fully under the hood OOP, but
we're able to pretty much at this point
emulate many of the features,
particularly now that there's private
data in the last couple of years. But
actually, instead of you want to follow
a functional paradigm, we're able to do
that, too. We can quite easily implement
most of the functional key features all
the way up to monads with JavaScript.
So, I do love that flexibility. I think
it's a huge edge, but only built on core
fundamentals.
Another thing that you mentioned that I
just want to make sure our listeners
understand, syntactic sugar. What does
syntactic sugar mean in the context of
JavaScript?
Yeah, a perfect example would be OOP,
object-oriented programming. So, this is
for many the essential design pattern
for building complex applications.
Allows you to think about things in a
structured way, to think about
properties that are universal,
properties that belong to the
subclasses, data that is shared between
different features, data that is not.
It's an extraordinary way to structure a
complex application. Okay, JavaScript
lets you do that, and it does it using a
architecture under the hood that is
absolutely not classical inheritance,
not classical object-oriented
programming. Instead, it uses a feature
called the prototype chain that allows
objects to access, I wouldn't even call
it inherit, but access functions and
features of other objects down a chain.
However, on the surface, the keywords
used, words like new or class, they are
very similar, they are identical to the
keywords used in natively
object-oriented languages that don't use
a chain model under the hood that gives
objects access to other functions, but
not direct inheritance as is built into
natively OOP languages. That creates a
lot of problems cuz when you use a new
keyword, if you're not aware that under
the hood it's creating an object inside
of the function you're calling with the
new keyword, it's adding any properties
you add to it using the keyword this is
access, it's automatically returning
that object out, but by the way, if you
call a function without the new keyword,
it's going to attach all those
properties to the native global object,
then you're going to look at JavaScript
and go, "What the heck? This doesn't
mirror anything that I know about OOP."
And so, your syntactic sugar tricks you
into thinking it's native OOP.
Essentially, it's a little bit of an
illusion. So, even though it looks like
OOP, it's not actually that. And you can
continue using it that way, but if you
understand how the internals work, you
can actually get the full benefit of the
way it's designed.
Correct?
Full benefit, but also have it not do
things you don't expect. So, in a
classical OOP language, you're not able
to use a constructor function without
the new keyword. In JavaScript, you
could use the very same function you
expect to be constructing an object
without a new keyword, and it will
create a new set of properties that
you've passed to that function, but
unfortunately, they'll be attached to
the default global object that's
available in JavaScript, and you won't
get an object returned out because the
new keyword will automate the process of
creating an object, adding properties,
and returning it out. The idea that that
is
being done not as a base level feature,
but as a syntactic sugar that's then
manually creating your object under the
hood, meaning you could still run that
function without the new keyword, and it
will try to add properties to its
default object, not the object you want
it to add, that creates a lot of
frustration in engineers. One of the key
questions that Google asked of any
engineer working with JavaScript, their
favorite question to ask was what's the
new keyword doing under the hood?
Because they know that that is, along
with how's closure work, essentially the
kind of tell me that you really
understand how this system is working.
Makes sense. Let's switch gears a little
bit because we are I think we are
halfway through the interview now. When
we talk about JavaScript, the word
engine gets bandied about a lot. When
JavaScript engineers talk about engine,
be it Google V8, be it Apple's
JavaScript core, SpiderMonkey, what are
they actually referring to in terms of
the stack? Is it a virtual machine, a
compiler, or something else?
It can be a number of things. I think
one thing to recognize is it is not the
entire web browser. It is a engine that
can be separately run in many
environments, both the web browser, but
also it can be directly run within your
core system as in Node, and therefore
has to be supplied with all the other
pieces you'd need if you're running on
your system directly, like ability to
have IO with the network. If you're in
the browser, it needs to be integrated
with the browser features. That's why
it's quite hard to pin down exactly what
we mean when we speak about an engine
because of course a V8 engine from
Google is integrated into the Chrome
browser. So, if you're working on the V8
engine, and there are opportunities to
optimize directly with the DOM or with
the web browser features, you're working
closely with the web browser developers.
And so, that's I think why it's quite
hard to pin down what people mean
exactly when they say engine because the
engine doesn't exist in isolation. In
fact, most of what we do in JavaScript
is writing code to interface with
features outside of the core engine. And
I think that's where a lot of the
development has happened as well. You
know, when we switched from XML HTTP
request to fetch, that is a web browser
feature, but one developed hand-in-hand
with the JavaScript engine team. I think
one that's particularly a shift for
quite seasoned engineers is the engine
has been very helpful at dealing with
dynamic code. So, adding properties to
an object at any time and knowing that
the engine will probably optimally treat
that in a way that is performant. That
can also lead, when those engine changes
happen, to anti-patterns. And I think
we're finally, this may be something
that your listeners are aware of, within
the just-in-time compiler, which is the
backbone of JavaScript engine from V8
from the Google team, the engine now
optimizes for what's called monomorphic
shapes. So, that's where your
object, as when defined, continues to
follow that pattern, that shape,
throughout its life cycle. And adding
properties then mid-execution breaks the
internal blueprint that's been built at
this just-in-time compilation stage and
then kills performance. So, that's the
challenge when thinking about engine
optimizations is you're firstly working
with an engine that is integrated within
a browser. So, even pinning down the
exact features of the engine requires
you to think about how it interacts with
the browser. But secondly, there are
changes only within the last year that
throw out what were considered
previously senior engineer best
practices. So, I think we're in a moment
of change there, and it's going to be
interesting to see how well communicated
it is. The JavaScript engine, at least
the V8 engine, now allows for
optimizations that you can
meta-programming style add as comments
that give information to the engine on
how it should approach the code. That's
something new and I think we're going to
see that play out and see how developers
pick it up.
Essentially, we're moving to sort of a
paradigm where the developer explicitly
instructs the engine as opposed to the
engine saving back code, which is how it
was in the olden days, right?
Correct.
Staying with that power engines give you
a lot more controls. Can you give us
some examples of the things that
developers can do in terms of how you
can instruct engine to be optimize one
thing or the other?
The main one is consistent monomorphic
classes or consistent monomorphic
objects. That is define your object and
define on it properties that will be
used even if currently null or undefined
to give the compiler the pre-programmed
shape for the object. Then do not add
properties dynamically afterwards
because at that point the blueprint that
gets created for the object has to be
thrown out. You know, the sort of the
fast rails to accessing that object, you
have to switch back to the slow rails.
That's honestly the main one that I'm
aware of.
Consistent monomorphic objects, just to
make sure I understand, that's
essentially a data structure that
maintains like a single unchanging shape
throughout its life cycle, right?
Correct. Exactly.
And having that, what does it change
things? How does it change an app or how
does it change the developer's
experience?
Honestly, what the V8 team
says is that
this allows more performant access to
object properties at runtime.
What it means for a developer is your
standard approach of treating an object
as a flexible data structure that you
can add or remove properties from
throughout your application's life cycle
becomes a sub-optimal approach. The
other features that JavaScript added, I
think, that are really interesting that
empower developers,
I do think that the symbol adds a whole
new set of tools for developers to
change how objects, iterators work at
the application level. And so, in the
hard parts workshop, I walked through
the the symbol principle, and it allows
you to manually override default
features of objects, of iterators to
follow patterns that you want. And
that's very empowering to engineers, the
chance to at the object level across all
within the library, change the behavior
to your particular target. That can be
anything from as trivial as logging an
object and having your own description
rather than object object, instead
having your own description that is
excellent for debugging, all the way
through to manually changing how
iterators, you know, a native feature of
JavaScript, iterate over an object or
iterate over a set of tasks. And that
metaprogramming ability, where you're
changing the behavior of JavaScript
without breaking the system, that's I
think a really interesting expansion of
what JavaScript does.
Looking for a way to stand out in a
competitive job market?
Whether you're trying to land your first
contributor role or prove you can
deliver, take the next step in your
career with the new software
professional certification from the IEEE
Computer Society.
Sign up today at
computer.org/certification.
So, essentially, you're creating a data
structure that's specific to your needs,
and you're tweaking the behavior of
underlying JavaScript functionality so
that it's optimized for that shape.
Correct. This becomes particularly
valuable though to library creators. So,
library creators are especially
sensitive that their library doesn't
break the code that people are using
their library in. And when they update
or, you know, release a new version,
they want to minimize the number of
changes that developers need to make to
ensure that they're like the new version
of the library works correctly. And so
for them to be able to add features a
genuinely as simple as having logging
expose a more relevant piece of
information than just object is
extremely valuable. So I think some of
these more uncommon features that have
been released in the last couple of
years, particularly symbols,
particularly valuable to library
developers. And I think that speaks to a
lot of where JavaScript has gone. You
know, as many people write JavaScript,
there are more people or at least as
many writing React. And I think that's
you know, it was funny I was talking to
an engineer a couple of days ago and he
said, "Is React the last framework?" Now
we already know there's new frameworks,
there's new approaches, but is React the
last framework? And at this point React
is so embedded that you can imagine for
the JavaScript team, one of their goals
is, "How can we ensure that React
developers, that is to say people
building the React library, are able to
continue to iterate and able to continue
to solve problems?" And can some of
these features that they've introduced
like symbols that give control to React
library creators, can those empower
developers indirectly via the React
library, you know, via the bun library
developers? Can we enable them to enable
developers in the community? And I think
that's what you look at some of the
JavaScript features as less serving the
broader developer community and more
serving the people building abstractions
on top of it that have become so
mainstream as to be thought of as almost
part of the JavaScript standard library
by proxy. So that's TypeScript, that's
React.
When you say library creators, that
phrase almost underplays what the
library creators are. Libraries we're
talking about are things like, you know,
Node.js, React, Vue.js. All these are
libraries, right? They're huge systems
in their own right. And when you're
talking about library creators, you're
talking about pretty much sometimes
entire companies or huge groups of open
source communities that are responsible
for maintaining these tools that we have
pretty much so many folks who live and
breathe these days.
And their core constraint is very
similar to JavaScript's, don't break the
web and don't break the code bases using
our library even as we want to add new
features. My kind of hypothesis is that
increasingly the JavaScript engine team,
you know, TC39 particularly, are
thinking in terms of those needs. Maybe
more than the engineers directly working
with JavaScript because most of the
population is working with those core
libraries.
So, the library creators, they have a
lot of power here in terms of using the
core features in the library itself, but
also encouraging users to experiment
with some of these features perhaps?
Yes. Look, we're not in the days of
Angular where the library artificially
created its own scope property, you
know, truly removing the JavaScript
layer entirely. We're actually in an age
where library developers love to use
native features as much as possible.
They love to surface native native
features as much as possible. I think
that's for a combination of three
things. One, performance, you know,
that's makes sense, might as well use
the native feature where you can. I
think two, it's in terms of people's
ability to understand and reason about
the problem. There's nothing like
creating an abstraction layer, you know,
a domain specific language. I often
thought of Angular as almost being a
domain specific language sitting almost
independent of JavaScript. I think the
only frameworks often did that. Creators
of React and no, they want to be able to
use the native features cuz it makes it
much more easy to reason about and they
are confident hopefully that people do
understand ES modules. They do
understand the asynchronous patterns
built into JavaScript. But the third
reason also I think is it makes for a
more transferable library. If your
library is such an abstraction layer on
top of the universal language of
JavaScript, then when you only want to
integrate it in a piece of your puzzle
and or want to have other libraries
integrate with it, the overhead is far,
far less than if you're building with a
library like the earlier versions of
Angular that just abstracted most of
JavaScript's core features. How do you
integrate Angular's scope variable into
a library that wants to work with
JavaScript's native scope scoping rules?
I think it's a very, very difficult. And
so, I think the third reason is library
creators benefit from their libraries
frameworks being as close to the metal,
as close to the core standard library
features as possible, because that is
just a massive developer maintenance
improvement.
And it improves interoperability, as you
just pointed out. Thank you for
clarifying that. I think it was
explained pretty clearly at that point.
I have to ask the mandatory AI question.
Given that everyone's using Cloud and
Gemini and other LLMs, can
code-generating LLMs accelerate the
transition to the Can they help folks
get better at JavaScript, or is it
effectively reinforcing legacy patterns,
because the training data set is
essentially really old userland code?
Yeah, I mean, that's another reason why
people think React is the last
framework, because for whatever reason,
the LLMs love React. I think the stories
of XML HTTP requests being the
recommended line of code, you know,
things that are 10-plus years old.
Although, by the way, no hard feelings
to XML HTTP request was a not a terrible
API, but I think Maybe it was a terrible
API. But, I think that
Let's not go there. Yeah, exactly.
I used to give talks on it, I guess. It
was very relieving when Fetch came
along. But, there's a couple of things
to say here. One is I don't really think
that the legacy code is the body of the
latest models. The latest models are
very well suited to at least relatively
recent, for more common codebases like
React, relatively recent, if not right
up-to-date approaches. Now, that doesn't
necessarily translate into codebases
that are less available in basically
GitHub repos, doesn't translate into the
companies' own internal patterns most of
the time. It certainly doesn't translate
into the ability to reason through what
the right architectural choice might be.
On the flip side, if you listen to
Andrej Karpathy, who, you know, you
could easily dismiss as somebody who
does a lot of talking online, that's
very kind of hyped on what AI agents can
do for coding. But, I think also as
somebody who's shown enormous commitment
to explaining under the hood how these
things are working, his conviction is
the models in the last 2 months have
reached a new level of performance. I
think that's probably fair. Now, that
being said, those are usually on
greenfield projects, and for large
legacy code bases with complex existing
standards and design patterns, my
question is less do they imply or
encourage patterns that are outdated,
and more do they discourage or people
lose the muscle to go under the hood,
which in the end, for those really
complex edge case challenges, remains a
vital part. You We're essentially moving
to two abstraction levels, and we think
about this when we're teaching, and I
think about this when I'm building
workshops or or my own development, is
moving between two abstraction levels,
one of which is within a given runtime,
understanding how a given feature, a
given line of code is really executing.
That may be something that you can get
the code snippet or have it automated,
but there will be moments where it's
not. But, simultaneously, you're working
at another abstraction level
increasingly, which is a system level,
where you're thinking about multiple
different runtimes, multiple different
network-connected devices, and you're
trying to orchestrate agents across all
of them, and have tasks completed. Those
two abstraction levels are so it almost
might be comparable to when we move from
languages that were heavy manual control
of memory allocation to more dynamic
languages, and having to work in both at
the same time. I think we have to think
in a a way, maybe more similar to 30-40
years ago when that transition was
happening, about what engineering means.
We have a higher-level abstraction where
we're working with agents and we're
evaluating their output, maybe literally
writing eval's to do so. And then we
have a lower-level abstraction, which it
might be a given runtime, where actually
exactly how the event loop works will be
the determining factor of whether your
code
functions or not. And no amount of
clawed agentic prompting will help you
make the optimal decision at the given
runtime level where a performance
problem emerges because you've not
understood how JavaScript automatic
garbage collection works and you've got
a memory leak because you've not really
understood how closure and how functions
associated memory is working and that
those are persistent even after they're
returned from another function. So, that
understanding at the runtime level to me
remains really crucial. So, for me, my
biggest emphasis for thinking about LLM
assisted coding is distinguishing,
building an under-the-hood understanding
of the given runtime simultaneously with
building an under-the-hood
under-the-hood understanding of the
system level runtime in which the agent
operates. And if you have both of those,
then you can tackle any problem. You can
tackle the agentic Ralph loop, you know,
that's supposedly running for 2 hours
but then bounces out and you can't work
out why. Oh, it's because the compaction
stage has cut the loop from your task.
And you can also work at the
runtime level where your function call
is still returning undefined because
you've not understood the order of code
execution because you don't understand
the event loop. So, I think it's under
the hood on both.
And I think the fact that it's such a
powerful tool to learn, right? Because
you could you could easily Before you'd
have to go and look at the API reference
or look at some textbook somewhere or,
you know, go look at Stack Overflow to
understand what's going on. Here you can
question it to see what went wrong, what
is the event loop. You can get an
under-the-hood understanding right then
and there, provided you put in the
effort to understand that. There you
could just prompt your way through and
you're like, "Just give me JavaScript to
do what I want. Take it, paste it, and
move on." Then you're not going to
understand it. But I guess if people put
in the effort to understand what's
happening under the hood, like you said,
at the system level and also at the
runtime level, your understanding of
what the powerful aspects of the
language would really grow.
And isn't that exciting? I love that
that's the still the edge.
100% but it's time.
[laughter]
Like, every software engineer now,
you've got to do so much. You've got to
do the system level stuff and you've got
to keep, you know, have multiple agents
doing so much of coding. How much do you
do and how much time do you set aside
becomes a challenge.
Oh my goodness. Yeah, I'm working on a a
hard parts at the moment of of agent
design. I think that is the new runtime.
That is the equivalent. It has the same
stuff. It has IO. It has a pointer,
essentially. It has memory, a context.
Pointer is executing. It's the LLM
interpreting the the next step to take.
And then it has IO, which may be across
multiple different components of a
system. And having a mental model of
that, in theory to me, much as having a
mental model that's pretty complete of a
programming runtime, should help
accelerate the ability to build
understanding. It's a sort of the
principles, the foundations that then
you can My goal always with JavaScript,
The Hard Parts, let's call it
Programming the Hard Parts, was if you
understand the underlying patterns, then
when a new feature is released or a new
library uses a feature you haven't used
before, you're able to unpick it because
you understand how the pieces under the
hood joined up. I think what we've not
yet had is that same sort of approach to
the agentic level because A, it's all
being worked out right now, and B, it
can appear to go a long way, a bit like
maybe JavaScript did for people. It can
appear to go a long way before you hit a
problem. But when you do, that's when
the system-level understanding under the
hood, I think will become priceless.
Is there an example that you'd like to
use about where this level of
understanding explicitly leads to a
measurable performance shift in some
tool that folks built when you teach?
Yeah, so I mean, I don't don't know if
you're thinking about the you know
agentic setting, but in the agentic
setting so we probably all heard about
the Ralph loop.
I mean in just you know conventional
heuristics just in terms of JavaScript
when it comes to instructing the engine
in those kind of places.
Yeah, I was giving a talk at BBC which I
adore. I'll put it on record. I really
really you know I live in California, I
live in San Francisco Bay Area and have
done for many years, but I continue to
feel you know great gratitude to the
best of the BBC. Obviously always
complications, but you know so I would
felt very lucky when I have given long
form courses to the BBC's engineering
team. And I gave the hard parts of
asynchronous programming. And an
engineer came up to me and said, "Hey, I
work on BBC iPlayer." So BBC iPlayer is
the UK's version of Netflix and has he
was describing 5 million concurrent
users at peak times if not probably far
more by now. And it's built on Node. And
he was sharing with me, "We've had this
persistent bug where we cannot work
out." And I can't remember the exact
details of it, but we cannot work out
how to
get our queuing essentially in order.
You know we're dealing with these 5
million concurrents across multiple
machines. And he I'd just walked through
there the event loop in Node. And in
Node it's even more complex than in
regular JavaScript which comes back to
that point that you were asking about
earlier about the engine design. In Node
again the engine is JavaScript joins up
quite closely with other bits. And so
the event loop while at the interface
between the engine and IO the sorry
environment in which it sits which might
be the browser it might be you know Node
and the system on the computer directly
has in JavaScript's version in the
browser you know so many queues. In
Node's it has something like six seven
different queues for asynchronous
function execution available. And
different types of tasks will be queued
up in different queues. And we know
about the micro task queue versus the
task queue, the callback queue, and
promises being placed or promise
associated functions being placed in the
micro task queue, and regular callbacks
in the callback queue. But in Node, I
mean, it's five or six or seven, there's
many, many queues, and each of them has
a different priority, and each of them
has a different behavior. And as I laid
out these different queues, he showed me
their code base and said, "We've been
using set timeout as a deferral
technique. We had a sense of, you know,
it seemed to be executing in the right
order, no understanding of why.
Understanding all these queues means we
can now from scratch properly implement
the order of execution that we want our
asynchronous code, the asynchronous or
delayed code to run at." And I was like,
"Oh, I felt very grateful that, you
know, this person who's working with
clearly small team running this vast
version of Netflix, BBC, you know, as a
tight-knit team because it's a publicly
owned organization, and has now the
ability to optimally work with their
asynchronous code in Node dealing with
something that's used by millions of
people. And so, just that under the hood
mental model opened up to him the
ability to optimize this really quite
significant code base. So, that was
always stuck with me as a moment where
having that mental model gives someone a
big edge.
That's a really cool example, especially
because I live in the UK now, and I play
it all the time.
[laughter]
Especially when I really like I have a
little child now, so when I just need to
switch off and watch some bizarre
documentary about like Lake District,
that's where I turn to. Netflix is no
match for that.
You know that under the hood, there is
code that is a result of people
understanding the event loop, you know,
in Node in full. So, yeah, that's cool.
Yeah.
100%. And that's beautiful, right? Like
when you build it just the right way,
using the perfect tool for the job, and
not just sort of, you know, any tool
that you can just pick up and totally
understand. That's beautiful. So, as an
engineer, I love that. So,
Yeah, totally.
I get your emphasis. Yeah. Staying on
folks listening in I anyone who works at
a large organization with JavaScript,
they're going to have to deal with the
refactoring question. If you have a
large code base and it's got a ton of
user land features and a thing
definitely a lot of JavaScript that can
be written better. What's the ROI on
refactoring and how do you think about
that? Like should you focus on the
performance wins or the maintenance
wins? How do you suggest people think
about that problem?
Yeah, I think it's maintenance win first
really. I think the performance win is
there, but you know, swapping moment for
temporal is a performance win no longer
downloading a 60 kilobyte library even
if it's you know, zipped or whatever
less, but you know, still not nothing,
but it's the removal of dependency
risks. You know, really you don't want
to have across your entire code base a
set of libraries that are you know,
maintained of course, but still
unpredictable versus the core features.
So I think really it comes down to
dependency time bombs. Syntax
optimization, it can't fix though even
if you do make those changes, what
really ends up being often the bigger
challenge architectural disaster, which
is things like as I said over fetching
massive JSON files. But so I I don't
think it's always the number one
priority of engineers to make these
changes, but when someone can remove a
library because they've identified that
enough of the core features and again,
that's where this temporal one comes in
so strongly because quality, time,
features have not been available in
JavaScript. If you're working with
anything serious, you needed a library
to work with it. That is going to
change. I'm not sure of the exact
release date. When I last gave hard
parts a few months ago, it wasn't yet
released. I think it was scheduled 2026,
but that's the kind of non-negotiable.
If you can now implement timing patterns
without needing an external library,
that's worth it, but primarily it's a
maintenance win. I think that's how you
have to think about these libraries and
in many cases that's going to be a you
know, company specific. If they are very
happy with a low-dash and many companies
are, then actually it could be more of a
maintenance cost to suddenly switch out
from it because while JavaScript now has
many of those array methods, it doesn't
have all of them. And low-dash still has
some library specific array methods that
JavaScript doesn't have. Well, if you
were all used to using low-dash, then
how much is it really a maintenance win
to switch to a function signature that
is different to low-dashes for your
reducing or mapping or flattening was
actually available to you in low-dash.
Many of those functions will have been
available in JavaScript long before the
company started using a helper library,
but they don't use them because they
follow the low-dash pattern throughout.
And so, it's to me often going to be a
case of I think you've hinted at this,
JavaScript is probably never going to
provide the full utility library because
it is a general use language. And so, if
you're then keeping your low-dash in,
then following that pattern for all your
array manipulations or all your data
manipulations is actually a better
maintenance win than switching out and
suddenly your developers are like, "Hold
on, which of these is a native function?
Which of these is a a low-dash
function?" So, I think that's often
going to be the case. I can't come back
to enough that date and time management
is one that JavaScript, I think, and
developers in general are really excited
to have natively. And I think you're
going to see a lot of switching out of
the moment libraries and equivalents
very soon.
And even if people don't switch out, at
least when they're building new apps or
new websites, they wouldn't start with
the low-dash or the moment. They'd start
with the temporal. And even if it's not
fully ready for prime time, you'd sort
of start playing with it now so that for
the new stuff, you don't want to be
using the using the libraries for sure.
Right.
And follow-up question there, given like
once temporal comes out, does moment
stop being supported? It's not like
moment support is going to stop anytime
soon, right?
No, exactly. So, I think it's fine. I
think it's compressed, very small
dependency. But, when you time as well
is a narrowly used feature. Whereas a
lot of these utility libraries are
embedded in every other line of code.
Every day.
I think it's much much harder to switch
out from those libraries and they're so
general use applicable. But that doesn't
really apply to something like time
which is mission critical when it's
there, but you know, it's much more
specific use cases.
Yeah, this has been really interesting.
To sort of close it off, I was going to
ask what do you expect in 2026 and what
are you excited about? I take it
temporal is definitely one of those.
Anything else in the JavaScript universe
that you're excited about in this year
and next year?
I'm excited to see what I would not have
expected, maybe I'm naive, but I would
not have expected that JavaScript would
build a native object cloning feature as
opposed to continue to rely on the JSON
approach. So, I'm curious to see what
other
native features will be introduced and
that we're not yet aware of. As you say,
temporal will be a a significant one. I
think it is hard to
unbundle
what happens in other languages. So, as
curious as I'm about where JavaScript
goes, I I am about where React and
TypeScript go. And I think React
shifting to at least a more balanced
take on server versus client-side
rendering is going to be really
interesting. One thing I think we have
to acknowledge is that as there are so
many environments in which JavaScript is
running emerge, one that I think is
particularly exciting is the Bun
environment.
What is that?
It is itself a a full JavaScript runtime
built from scratch, but it has around it
a built-in package manager, bundler,
test runner. So, it can replace Node,
but it's very thoughtfully designed to
the point that as I, you know, use
agentic workflows, it's you might
default using Python. With Bun, you
might actually get a more readable
interface than you would with Python.
obviously, you know, Python is always
almost always the most readable
interface and certainly more than node.
And I think that's really exciting. So,
when I'm building an I've got a workshop
coming up building an agent from
scratch. So, sort of building an open
claw implementation from scratch for
people to get an under the hood
understanding of it and I'm using Bun as
the environment as the runtime and
environment where I'd normally think
about using Python and probably not node
because I think it's just too you know,
too much of an emphasis on you know,
essentially server design. Whereas here
we're talking about a more flexible
environment for JavaScript to run in
that feels a lot more like using Python
on your machine. And that's really
exciting. So, I think that's seeing
JavaScript and it's a it is a JavaScript
engine and Bun built from scratch super
performant, but it's also a JavaScript
engine sitting within, you know, it's
package management, it's environment.
And I think we're going to see more of
JavaScript as a as a full environment
that will end up as a user chord or as
you build an agent being a backbone for
it. It might even be that while we think
that for work that's going to happen on
your machine rather than the browser you
default to Python, somehow JavaScript
might continue to survive as the core
language even of agentic workflows that
sit much less in the browser. I think
that'd be really intriguing if that were
to happen.
I mean, I think of Bun as something like
a Swiss Army knife where it replaces a
bunch of different tools and it's much
faster than Node.
Who would have expected that JavaScript
might survive the transition to agentic
driven engineering?
Let's wait till agentic really comes.
[laughter]
You can't take anything for granted.
Now, as we joke around here, like the
next 3 years is just like, you know, you
never know what's going to happen.
What's going to stay, what's going to
change, we'll have to wait and see.
The next 3 months.
3 months exactly.
This has been a really interesting
conversation. Thank you so much for
taking the time. Before we sort of
finish up, any question that I didn't
ask that I should have asked?
The only thing would be what does the
shift in the abstraction layer mean for
engineering as a whole? And and I think
that it's worth for all the software
engineers listening who might be feeling
an ambivalence, you know, you move up an
abstraction layer, what about all the
craft that was developed for
understanding the you know, the runtime
that you know, and A I think it remains
very important. Any real production
environment is so full of edge cases
that require the ability of a human to
convert the complex need into a specific
implementation. But then secondly, the
next abstraction level up, let's call it
a gentic, is one that also requires
complex reasoning. It orchestration
describes, you know, complex reasoning
about moving parts, but also one that
can then be applied to new domains. And
that's why I'm working in you know,
what's called embodied AI or physical
intelligence, where increasingly the key
workflows are ones that are very
familiar to software engineers rather
than roboticists. And it's model
pipelines, it's imitation learning, it's
what's called VLAs, which allow you to
treat the output of a robot as a
software problem. And I think that's
very exciting that many of these same
mental models and principles of an
engineer, a software engineer, are going
to apply to domains that we didn't think
were software engineering domains. I I
always come back to the fact that the
Nobel Prize for Chemistry won by Sir
Demis Hassabis, a software engineer, a
game developer as his first job. And
that's for something that is now pivotal
for drug discovery and specifically
protein folding, but to me other
consequences. And so I think it's an
exciting time to be a software engineer,
and I think many of us can feel some
ambivalence about that as things change
so fast, but the mental models and the
ability to go under the hood and reason
about complex systems will apply to
whole new domains that we didn't
previously think we had access to. And
so that's what I'm excited about on a
personal level.
Thank you for that. It's a really
inspiring way to end the podcast, end
the session. And you're right, there is
a lot of ambivalence, there is a lot of
fear with how things are changing, but
taking the time to understand how things
work and really understand how things
work under the hood is something that
will never go out of fashion. And
investing in that is the right way
forward. So, thank you for a really
interesting conversation. We hope to
speak in the future about one of the
other interesting things that you're
working on.
Thank you so much, Adi. I really
appreciate being part of this.
Thank you so much.
[music]
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
[music]
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website, or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.